all right this is the first video in the
Scythian series and I guess by nature is
gonna be a little bit broader than is
appropriate for this particular kind of
venue is that to prime pad at least a
little bit of context is what I'm
talking about
hopefully in the future we'll actually
be able to go back and recreate this
particular video to be more I guess
specific so context the notion of the
CDM project is based upon a I guess a
premise and a possibility so the premise
is that the the city is foundational to
the nature of what I've called game a or
to the fundamental basis of the toolkit
that gives rise to the kinds of
civilizations the human beings of this
far been able to create so I'm making a
proposition that city is more
fundamental than civilization the
possibility that I am proposing is that
we are now within a threshold we are now
near to a point we can in fact innovate
a new way living together that is
different it's a different basis than
the city and there for and thereby that
transition is fundamental it moves us
from one basis that gives rise to entire
architecture of civilizations to
potentially a very different one which
if we wanted to use that language we
could say game Bay although I suppose a
bit about that these days
so nobody get into the into the depth of
this particular piece this piece is
about about the first proposition and
some of the context around that and to
do that I have to go into a little bit
of depth so this video is probably gonna
be on the road of like 10 or 12 minutes
I apologize for the length the the core
theory here comes from work that was
done largely around the Santa Fe
Institute largely with people like
Geoffrey West and we spent court and
many others and you can read about it
actually in the book called scale the
Geoffrey West produced the past couple
of years and I'll just give the a brief
summary kind of compress the piece that
I think is most relevant what they were
looking at was particular
characteristics that are called scaling
loss which is to say if I if I increase
some particular characteristic
like let's say for example I have a one
brick and that brick weighs one pound
and I increase one characteristic so I
increase from one brick to ten bricks so
this gives an increasing number how many
pounds do I have well in the case of
bricks it's a linear scaling loss if I
have gone from one brick to ten bricks
I've gone from one pound to ten dollars
and they were looking at various all
kinds of different systems in nature
looking at what kinds of scaling laws
were there what they found was that
there was a very profound fundamental
that in many important characteristics
like for example the ratio between body
mass and metabolism or body mass and
like amount of vascular tissue like how
long would your vascular system if you
kind of could lay it all out and measure
it that there was a an extraordinary
regularity of what are called sub linear
scaling laws and very specifically in
fact xx 5 which is to say for example if
I have a mouse that weighs 100 grams and
I and it has a metabolic rate X and I
double its mass to 200 grams I don't in
fact double it its metabolism in fact
right because my a hundred percent
increase it by only eighty-five percent
more or less like I'm just trying to
brush broad brush into the zone here and
this the sub linear scaling is very
fundamentally characteristic you might
even see it's at the very heart of
living systems specifically dissipative
systems I think but in any event living
systems so with you looking at cells or
organisms we're looking at mammals or
reptiles whether you're looking at by
the way trees or forests right entire
ecosystems that are multi species you
still see these seen this exact same
kind of sub linear scaling dynamic and
that's huge is it's an enormous ly
important finding and it talks about for
example how systems have limits to
growth built in elephants are kind of as
big as they're going to get blue wheels
are as big as they're going to get in
the context of that particular niche for
example and when they wouldn't started
looking at human systems they found the
human systems also more or less and we
give you the exception a minute fell
under the same rule
so if I take a corporation and I add
more people I don't for example increase
revenue per person linearly actually
increases on kind of like a asymptote so
when I go from a thousand people to two
thousand people I don't double the
revenue per person in fact I attend to
actually each per capita input reduces
which means that corporations have a
natural asymptote at a certain point
you're just not getting any more
productivity out of the individuals that
you're adding into the system we also
see in for example cities that if you
take a look at the population of a city
and you look at for example the length
of roads in the city or the sort of
length total measure of say telephone
lines or or sewers the same basic
characteristic if I double the
population of a city the the amount of
the length of roads does not double it
increases by eighty five percent okay
that's cool so what's that saying is
these human built systems are very much
like biological systems so a city is
like in in this context a city is like a
forest but and this but is the point of
this video frankly the entire series to
be perfectly frank with regard to other
characteristics cities and only in
cities did they find not just not a sub
linear scaling metric but a super linear
scaling metric so what that means what
it meant was that with regard to
something like say income per capita so
I've got a city of a million everybody
makes let's just say on average ten
thousand dollars a month if I double the
population of the city the per capita
income goes up by about fifteen percent
so it's 115 so instead of everybody
making $10,000 a month now everybody
makes eleven thousand five hundred now
this is a very important thing because
it means that if I'm choosing between
city a and City B and City a is a five
hundred thousand person city and city B
is a million person city then on average
just me being exactly the same nothing
about me I will make more money going to
city be 15% were hardly enough and by
the way if there's a city see it's a 2
million person city on average I'll make
more money go into cities see now of
course what that means is that more
likely I will choose the biggest city
which means the biggest cities gonna
tend to get bigger and here it is the
very powerful thing in some very strong
sense
cities are to people like stars are to
atoms there's a desire sometimes a
gravitational tractor to pack as many
people as possible into the city because
if you increase the population then you
increase things like wealth and by the
way also innovation so this gives rise
to a very powerful dynamic just like a
star by the way where a star kind of
wants to collapse to a singularity from
the point of view of gravity and then
it's pushing against the electro Matic
magnetic force that prevents the atoms
from getting any closer together they
can and that gives you the dynamic of
the star cities have the attractor of
wanting to get more people in the city
to increase the wealth and innovation
and other variables and it's facing the
repulsor of for example constraints
around but for one thing people have
physical bodies so they have to be in
space there's only a storm to kill you
can pack into a particular piece of
space or giving them food but there's
only so much food you could produce in
the city if you're producing the food
out of the city you've got
transportation so if you can only walk
for example then there's no so far you
can bring food and water etc and also
moving waste out of the city as
constraints and so we see is a kind of a
seeking on the part of cities to
maximally use the technology that is
available to them to overcome the
limitations or the constraints of
physical bodies to pack as many human
beings as possible into cities to
thereby get this super linear growth in
wealth and innovation and other
characteristics and then effectively
running into the limits of that so the
Romans could build aqueducts but the
Babylonians couldn't build off so they
had a limit when we invented the a the
elevators something could go up past
three or four floors
what people
reasonably walk on stairs and something
build skyscrapers in fact a lot more
people into the same space and okay next
piece this piece is by the way
substantially more let's call it
theoretical I'm extending this out you
creates fragility so the city is
endeavouring to spring as many people
into it notice that as it brings more
people in it gets more wealth and it
gets more innovation so it has the
capacity to start trying to figure out
how to solve problems so again there was
a point at which Rome couldn't bring
enough water in but they can figure out
how to build aqueducts they build these
aqueducts and pull water from hundreds
of miles away to be able to continue to
support the population now here's a
proposition the proposition is
effectively the entire population of a
region is composed of the city and its
support infrastructure and so the
hypothesis is that the city is trying to
get as many people as possible into the
center and literally everything that
isn't in the center is just support
infrastructure so if you look at the
contemporary Western world in particular
you see something that looks like that
you've got giant cities that have sort
of evaporated the population out of it
out of their local environment but it's
sort of population deserts except for
the location that can provide support
infrastructure and in some cases that
support infrastructure has to do with
locations where people who really don't
want to be in cities can still be okay
and then what happens is is that the
dynamic of packing more and more people
and pushes it to the limits which means
that is optimizing for the capacity to
increase the number of people in the
city which means that it's becoming
fragile logistics it's as intense as it
can food distribution gets as intense as
it can water distribution gets its
intensity as it can you're also running
into situations where by the way things
like crime and disease also tend to
increase super linearly so you have to
build techniques to try to reduce that
visa fee innovation innovation welfare
fighting against crime and disease and
so minor perturbation as the system
becomes more and more optimized for
maximizing population your particular
constraints of technology
boom you gotta collapse and then that
collapse creates a collapse of the
entire civilization so by hypothesis for
example I would propose that the
collapse of the Roman Empire wasn't some
very distinct sense the actual collapse
of the city of Rome and everything else
was support infrastructure now that's a
pretty bold claim and I don't
necessarily need to hang my hat too much
on that last piece but the key idea here
is city attraction repulsion dynamic has
being fundamental to the nature of
civilization until now because if you
think about it if you look at it deeply
what you might say what I'm proposing is
that the core attractor is actually not
the city the dynamic is actually more
abstract and what we've seen in the city
is really just the fact that bodies are
human beings in bed and bodies the thing
that really wants to happen the thing
the real driver of the super linear
scaling metric is Minds in relationship
intelligence distinct intelligence is
interacting through some mechanism and
it's because minds are embodied that we
have cities up until very recently the
only way for minds to interact if you
had bring bodies relatively close to
each other and those are subject to the
constraints of effectively travel and
now more recently telecommunications the
telecommunications has been relatively
weak like a telegraph telephone
television these various kinds of media
that Korea the possibility of
interaction relationship over
non-physical distances have changed
things a lot but they still haven't been
strong enough to overcome the
possibility for relationship that exists
in physical proximity but now it looks
like you may be either at or near the
tipping point where things like this
medium and more importantly things like
video conferences and I strongly suspect
the next wave of virtual reality have
enough possibility of relationship in
the virtual that we can in fact decouple
the attractor and the repulsion so thus
idiom is a concept based on that premise
the CVM is a concept that says
if we can render unto the virtual what
is best done in the virtual and render
into the physical what is best under the
physical and then bring those back into
proper relationship we can change the
whole game so what do I mean what I mean
is creative generative collaboration in
the virtual and now here we can't in
fact have a single city one place for
all minds at least in principle can be
in right relationship with each other
they can communicate they can
interrelate no longer constrained in the
same way by physicality and by the way
this also means that we have to be
thinking very clearly about what are the
right ways to bring those minds into
relationship how do we actually build
this virtual environment so it's
maximally generative there's a whole new
space we have to take this seriously not
because it's going to be not an adjunct
to civilization but a fully symmetric
basis to civilization with the physical
side now by the way this implies that we
should get significant increases in
wealth and innovation if I can take the
biggest cities in the world and increase
them by what about seven or eight
doublings I'm increasing wealth by a lot
so for example if I were to take the
population of Tokyo and now move that to
include the entire human population the
average income would go up by about 3 or
5 X there's a lot ok so that's one side
on the other side when I have made this
decoupling and now bided are not being
squeezed together because the body is
the substrate for relationship now the
bodies can be returned to humaneness to
a more humane way of living living in
the tomorrow limit you're living among
people who you know well strong link
relationships family community living in
nature making sure that the place that
you're living is built at human scale
very walkable very quiet low toxicity
where you always have relationship with
being in the earth being in nature and
and and by the way I suspect that this
is not just awesome I know not only does
it does it I'll give us back a whole
bunch of values that we've had to give
up in the context of the the gluttony of
the city
I suspect it's actually going to be
obligate to enable the virtual to be as
powerful as it needs to be so for
example imagine most people now are
experiencing the fact that interaction
via the virtual like we would say for
example in a zoom conference is
substantially more draining than
interaction in the physical mind if I if
I'm in a room of 12 people I'm having a
conversation with 12 people for me at
least as an introvert it's very draining
but it's training us can say X but if I
have that same length of conversation
with those same 12 people but it's all
in a zoom call it is substantially more
draining let's say 2x it's more like 5x
but whatever now imagine if when you
finish that zoom conference instead of
dropping back into your body in the
context that you're in now you dropped
into a context that is extremely
nurturing for human beings you were able
to go sit under a shade tree next to
running water maybe you can swim in the
water or he could go out and interact
with people with whom you have very
healthy relationship and do something
together like build a wall or dig in the
garden or whatever it happens to be the
debate is very human
how much more grounding that is and
returns your nervous system back to a
state of health so that you can then
cycle back into the virtual and extend
that creativity in their generativity
like this movement between the virtual
and the physical now becomes something
that we can breathe a couple Reed couple
in a right way and get a lot more out of
it and a lot more out of it that is
healthy so that's the notion all right
so the idea here is that we can take
this incredibly powerful generator of
wealth and innovation that has been
captured in the city which has a whole
bunch of characteristics of forcing us
into situations that are increasingly
inhumane not healthy for humans and pop
that apart and increase it by a factor
of 5 to 7 at the virtual level so get
something more generative than the
cities that have dreamed of being but at
the same time recover and get back all
of the human scale living that we've had
to surrender and return to that sort of
wholesomeness of life the many of us I
think you're in for and
here we are eyewear we're in that pivot
point the quarantine has shown us
whether we like it or not
that many of the things that we have had
to wear these have thought we had to do
in interaction you know work environment
learning environments much of that can
be done virtually in fact depending on
how the next several months play out
much of it will continue to have to be
done virtually so we're going to be
having to learn in those skills and this
gives rise to an opportunity to extend
into that into the experiment and see
hmm
okay what does that look like if we make
that fundamental and that's we're doing
18 minutes pretty long probably shoot
this again in a different frame and see
if I can make it shorter but but those
who chose to watch this to the end I
hope it was worth it